A Guide to the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1838-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series 1: Literary Manuscripts
  - "Leaves of Grass," 1857-1871, 230 leaves, handwritten (Bowers #31). (Folders 50-51)
    - Pages 95-163, Volume 2: Ungrouped Poems, 1857-1859, 56 leaves.
      - "France, the 18th Year of These States," pages 123-127, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 5 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm. to 22.5 x 13.5 cm.
        On five leaves of pink paper (all between 21-22.5 x 13-13.5 cm.), in black ink, with heavy revisions in the same ink, in fine pen (blacker ink), in pencil, and in light ink. Multiple pinholes in center, and a few in left margin, of each leaf. Originally numbered 86; Whitman also numbered the leaves 1-5 (in pencil, lower left corner), with the 1 replacing a 6 and the 2 written over what looks like a 7. The leaves correspond to the 1860 published version France,/ The 18th Year of These States as follows: leaf 1 to numbered sections 1 through 2 (verses 1-3); leaf 2 ("I was not so deadly/ sick...") to sections 2 (verses 4-5) through 4 (verse 1); leaf 3 ("I myself keep the blaze,") to sections 4 (verses 2-5) through 5 (verses 1-3); leaf 4 ("And from to-day, sad and/ cogent,...") to verses 4-8 of section 5; and leaf 5 ("O I think now/ The east wind...") to the remaining four verses of section 5. Although Whitman never changed the title, and did not revise the poem much, he did transfer it twice, grouping it in the cluster Songs of Insurrection within the main body of Leaves in 1872 and 1872, and in 1881 finally transferring it to the new cluster Birds of Passage within Leaves.
        - Page 123, Volume 2. "France the 18th year of these States"
        - Page 124, Volume 2. I was not so deadly sick
        - Page 125, Volume 2. I myself keep the blaze
        - Page 126, Volume 2. And from today, sad and
        - Page 127, Volume 2. O I think now
        - Page 128, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "France," verse 4, verse 5.
      - "Unnamed Lands," pages 129-133, Volume 2: 5 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm. 1857-1859, 5 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
        On five leaves of pink paper (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in a blacker ink (fine and thicker pen), and in light ink. Originally numbered 81, with the note "?/(Leaf of)" above the number and title. Whitman numbered the leaves 1-5 in pencil in the lower left corners. Pinholes in center and left margin of each leaf. The leaves correspond to the numbered sections of the 1860 published version (same title) as follows: leaf 1 to section 1 (verses 1-6); leaf 2 ("What of liberty and slavery/ among them,") to the remaining three verses of section 1 and to section 2; leaf 3 ("Afar they stand—yet near/ to me they stand,") to section 3; leaf 4 ("Are they gone? those/ billions of men?") to sections 4 through 5; and leaf 5 ("I believe that was not the/ end of those nations") to section 6. In the 1872 Leaves Whitman transferred the poem to a Leaves of Grass group, and in 1881 it was finally moved, after several revisions through the different published versions, to the cluster Autumn Rivulets.
        - Page 129, Volume 2. "Unnamed Lands"
        - Page 130, Volume 2. What of liberty and slavery
        - Page 131, Volume 2. Afar they stand-yet near
        - Page 132, Volume 2. Are they gone? those
        - Page 133, Volume 2. I believe that was not the
        - Page 134, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Unnamed Lands"
        - Page 135, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Unnamed Lands," continued.
      - "Kosmos," Pages 136-137, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 21.5 x 12.5 cm.
        On two leaves of pink paper (21.5 x 12.5 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in pencil, in blacker ink, in fine pen (very black ink), and in light ink. Originally numbered 55. Pinholes in center and left margin. Leaf 1 corresponds to verses 1-6 of the 1860 version, and the lines on leaf 2 ("Who out of the theory of the/ earth,...") correspond to verses 7-10. Revised very little through the different editions, Kosmos appeared in 1872 and 1876 in a Leaves of Grass group in the supplement Passage to India. In 1881 it was finally transferred to the cluster Autumn Rivulets within the main body of Leaves.
        - Page 136, Volume 2. "Kosmos"
        - Page 137, Volume 2. Who out of the theory of the
        - Page 138, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Kosmos"
        - Page 139. 1860 edition as published: "Kosmos," continued.
      - "A hand-mirror," Page 140, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
        On one leaf of pink paper (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in a fine pen (blacker ink) and light ink, including the title. Originally titled Looking-Glass and numbered 82. A few pinholes in center and left margin. This poem was titled but ungrouped until 1881, when Whitman finally placed it in the cluster By the Roadside.
      - Page 141, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "A Hand-Mirror"
      - "Savantism," page 142, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
        On one leaf of pink paper (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in a fine pen (blacker ink) and pencil. Only two or three pinholes in center. Originally numbered 52. Ungrouped in the 1860 and 1867 Leaves, this poem, according to Bradley and Blodgett, was transferred to Passage to India in 1871 and from there to Leaves of Grass groups in the Passage to India annexes of the 1872 Leaves and the 1876 Two Rivulets. From there it was moved, finally (in 1881), to the Inscriptions cluster within the main body of Leaves.
      - Page 143, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Savantism"
      - "Says," pages 144-148, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 5 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 12.5 cm. to 21.5 x 13 cm.
        On five leaves of pink paper (all between 21 and 21.5 x 12.5 and 13 cm.), in black ink, with extensive revisions in the same ink, in pencil, and in fine pen (very black ink). Multiple pinholes in center, and a pair at top, of each leaf. These poems were revised to form numbered sections of the ungrouped poem Says in the 1860 edition of Leaves. According to Bradley and Blodgett, Whitman cut four verse paragraphs in the 1867 Leaves version; from that point on the shortened poem appeared, ungrouped, under the title Suggestions until its final appearance in 1876. Leaf 1: originally numbered 85. Verses 3 and 4 went unpublished, but 1-2 and 5 became sections 1, 2, and 3 (verse 1) of the 1860 version. Leaf 2, [I say the least developed/ person on earth...]: these lines became sections 3 (verse 2) and 4, with the second line remaining unpublished. Leaf 3, 87—/ Say. [I say the human shape/ or face is so great,...]: first numbered 86. This became section 5. On the verso appears the deleted line "And though I lie dead." Leaf 4, 88—/ Say.— [I say the word of a land/ fearing nothing—...]: first numbered 86, then 87. This leaf became section 6. Leaf 5, 89—/ Say [I have said many times/ that materials...]: this leaf was originally numbered 88 and titled Thought, with two verses that Whitman deleted along with the first title. Below a horizontal pencil line he inscribed, at some point, verses that became section 7 of Says in 1860.
        - Page 144, Volume 2. "Says"
        - Page 145, Volume 2. I say the least developed
        - Page 146, Volume 2. "Say (I say the human shape)"
        - Page 147, Volume 2. "Say (I say the word of a land)"
        - Page 148, Volume 2. "Say (I have said many times)"
        - Page 149, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Says"
        - Page 150, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "Says," continued.
      - "Nearing Departure," page 151, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 2 pages on 1 leaf, handwritten, 16 x 20 cm.
        On the first and third sides of a folded leaf of white wove paper (16 x 20 cm.), in light ink, with minor revisions in the same ink. A few pinholes in the upper left corner when folded up. Whitman retitled the poem To My Soul in the 1860 edition of Leaves. The first inscribed page corresponds to numbered sections 1 through 3, verses 1-3, of the 1860 version, and the second ("The unspeakable love I inter-/changed with women,") to section 3, verses 4-13. In 1867 Whitman cut eight lines and revised others, retitling the poem As Nearing Departure and moving it to an untitled group of poems in the supplement Songs Before Parting. In 1872 it was finally retitled As the Time Draws Nigh and transferred to the cluster Songs of Parting within the main body of Leaves.
      - Page 152, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "To My Soul"
      - "So Long!," pages 153-159, Volume 2: 1857-1859, 7 leaves, handwritten, 15 x 9 cm.
        On seven leaves of blue lined laid paper, three of them composite leaves, with leaf 7 including a paste-on of white wove paper. Multiple pinholes in center of each leaf. Whitman numbered the leaves 75-81 in the upper right corner, with the exception of leaves 6 and 7, which are numbered at top center. In tiny script and various inks, with very heavy revisions, as follows. Leaf 1: plain leaf (15 x 9 cm.) in medium-black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in pencil, in fine pen (very black ink), and in light ink. Corresponds exactly in terms of the number of lines used to the first page of the poem as published (under the title So long! ) in the 1860 Leaves. This first page comprised numbered sections 1 through 3, verses 1-6. Leaf 2 ("When fathers, firm, unconstrained, nonchal-/ant, open-eyed—..."): plain leaf (15 x 9 cm.), in medium-black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in pencil, and in the fine pen (very black ink). Corresponds to sections 3 (verses 7-8) through 7 (verse 1) in the 1860 version. Leaf 3 ("Once more I proclaim the whole of/ America..."): plain leaf (15 x 9 cm.), in medium-black ink, with revisions in the same ink and in pencil. Corresponds to sections 7 (verse 2) through 10, along with section 12, in the 1860 version. On the verso appear two deleted sections, comprising nine verses (beginning "Yet, old throat, one loud/ cadenza!") revised from the bottom of original leaf 4, which Whitman compressed and reversed on the leaf 4 paste-on to eventually form sections 15 and 16 in the published version. Leaf 4 ("I announce the continued union of/ The States,"): composite leaf measuring 15 x 9 cm., with a faded blue paste-on of 5.5 x 9 cm. covering several water- damaged and heavily revised verses on the original leaf. In medium-black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in a slightly browner ink (thicker pen), in pencil, in fine pen, and in light ink. Corresponds to sections 11 and 13-16 of the 1860 version. Leaf 5 ("Screaming electric, the atmosphere using,"): plain leaf (15 x 9 cm.), in medium-black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in pencil, and in light ink. Corresponds to section 17 in the 1860 version. Whitman cut up a deleted earlier pink-paper draft of the first three verses for use as a paste-on in the poem Thought (section 9 of Chants Democratic in the 1860 Leaves; see 2:1:3). On the verso appear heavily revised draft verses, in pencil and only partly deleted, for sections 22 and 23. Leaf 6 ("What is there more that I lag and pause?"): full leaf (15 x 9 cm.) with six paste-ons in light ink and black ink, and with heavy revisions in the same inks and in pencil. The final paste-on corresponds to sections 18-20 of the 1860 version, but the other paste-ons and the original leaf contain drafts for the rest of the poem (sections 21-23). Leaf 7 ("O how your fingers drowse me!"): full leaf (15 x 9 cm.) with two paste-ons, the first a large section (13 x 9 cm.) of the same blue paper and the second a small section (6.5 x 10.5 cm.) of white wove paper. The white paste-over is inscribed in light ink with no revisions; the blue paste-over is inscribed in medium-black ink, with extensive revisions in pencil and in the same ink, as with the deleted verses on the original page. The white paste-on corresponds to section 21 in the 1860 version, and the blue paste-on contains the latest draft of what would become sections 22 and 23. In 1860 this was the final poem in Leaves; in 1867 Whitman cut twenty-one lines (according to Bradley and Blodgett) and transferred it to the end of the last Leaves supplement Songs of Parting. In 1872, with the transformation of this supplement into the cluster Songs Before Parting, it was permanently fixed as the final poem in the main body of Leaves.
        - Page 153, Volume 2. "So Long!"
        - Page 154, Volume 2. When fathers, firm, unconstrained, nonchal-
        - Page 155, Volume 2. Once more I proclaim the whole of
        - Page 156, Volume 2. I announce the continued union of/ The States
        - Page 157, Volume 2. Screaming electric, the atmosphere using
        - Page 158, Volume 2. What is there more that I lag and pause
        - Page 159, Volume 2. O how your fingers drowse me
        - Page 160, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "So long!"
        - Page 161, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "So long!" continued.
        - Page 162, Volume 2. 1860 edition as published: "So long!" continued.
      - "Sparkles from the Wheel," page 163, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 2 pages on 1 leaf, handwritten, 25.5 x 20 cm.
        First published not in the 1860 Leaves but in a Leaves of Grass group in the separate publication Passage to India in 1871. On two leaves (25.5 x 20 cm.) of thick, ruled, white laid paper joined with paste in the left margin. In black ink with revisions in the same ink and in pencil. Whitman penciled in the note "Long Primer/ middling wide measure" in the upper left corner of the first leaf, and on the verso of the second wrote and deleted (also in pencil) the note "The worship of God is, honoring his gifts/ in other men, each according to his genius, &/ loving the greatest men best. Those who/ envy or calumniate great men, hate God/ William Blake[.]" After being bound with the rest of the Passage to India poems as a supplement to Leaves of Grass, in 1881 this was permanently transferred to the cluster Autumn Rivulets within the main body of Leaves.
    - "Fables," page 164, Volume 2. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 23 x 20 cm.
      On one leaf (23 x 20 cm.) of thick, ruled white laid paper, in medium-black ink, with minor revisions in pencil and in the same ink. This became numbered verse paragraph 4 of section 2 of the title poem in the separate 1871 publication Passage to India. In 1881 the poem Passage to India was transferred, ungrouped, to the main body of Leaves.
  - Proposed table of contents for "Leaves of Grass," on verso of "To An Exclusive." (Box-folder 1:52)
  - . Leaves of Grass & Two Rivulets: Draft of Advertisement for Centennial Edition, 1876, AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 11 cm. x 18.5 cm., mounted. #3829-a. (Box-folder 1:53)
    Note in folder states that for the centennial of the United States WW had 100 Centennial Editions of Leaves printed, which he then sold in a booth at the Centennial Celebration in Philadelphia. Written in ink. With typed transcription.
  - "Living Pictures" on same leaf as "A cluster of poems." (Box-folder 1:54)
  - "Lo, where arise three peerless stars...," 1886 April 19, AMsS, 1 p. on 1 l. #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:55)
    From "Thou Mother With Thy Equal Brood," verse 6.
  - "Marked Hollandic Elements," [ca. 1881?], AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten. #9778. (Box-folder 1:56)
    Whitman, in third person, describes the ethnic heritage of his mother and father which contributes to the writing of Leaves of Grass. Written on verso of an autograph seeker's letter. See McGregor Autograph Collection, Box 8.
  - "Memoranda of a Year," 1863, AMs, 3 pp. on 2 l., Barrow. #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:57)
  - "My Picture Gallery," n.d., AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 10 x 15.5 cm., mounted. #3829 (Bowers #26). (Box-folder 1:58)
    On one fragment (10 x 15.5 cm.) of white wove paper, in brown-black ink, with extensive revisions in the same ink and in pencil. The pencil notes "? for children" and "extend this/?" appear in the upper left corner. The final verse, also in pencil, appears in the upper right corner. There are also two or more ink squiggles on the leaf. Originally titled Pictures, this is a revision of the first four verses of a draft poem by that name, inscribed by Whitman in a twenty-nine page notebook before the first edition of Leaves appeared in 1855. (The Pictures notebook is currently housed at Yale University.) Bradley and Blodgett note that after further revision Whitman published these verses in the October 30, 1880 issue of The American under the title My Picture-Gallery, after which he placed it in the new cluster Autumn Rivulets in the 1881 edition of Leaves.
  - "The Mystic Trumpeter," [ca. 1872], AMs draft, 9 pp. on 9 l., handwritten, 25 x 19.5 cm. #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:59)
    On nine leaves of different types of white paper, all measuring roughly 25 x 19.5 cm., described individually as follows. Other drafts of the poem are housed in the Charles E. Feinberg Collection at the Library of Congress, the Trent Memorial Collection at Duke University, and the T.E. Hanley Collection at the University of Texas. The Mystic Trumpeter was first published in the February 1872 issue of The Kansas Magazine, after which Whitman published it in the 1872 book As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free, in Two Rivulets (1876), and in the 1881 edition of Leaves of Grass. There and in later editions of Leaves the poem was included in the cluster From Noon to Starry Night. Leaf 1: on the verso of a sheet of laid, gray-ruled Department of Justice letterhead, dated "Washington...187[ ]" (see leaves 2 and 8). Inscribed in black ink, with extensive revisions first in pencil and then in black ink. This is a later draft than leaf 2 of verses that would eventually constitute the first numbered section of the poem. Whitman's number "1" appears in orange crayon in the upper right corner of the leaf. Leaf 2 ("Hark! some wild trumpeter—some/ strange musician!"): also on the verso (upside-down) of a leaf of the same Department of Justice letterhead. Inscribed in black ink, with heavy revisions in the same ink, then in pencil and in fine pen (original ink?). Whitman deleted most of the lines, drafting them again and shifting many of them around on leaf 1. Leaf 3 ("Come nearer mystic/ trumpeter"): on a composite leaf formed by pasting a small section (8 x 12 cm.) of unruled laid paper to a full sheet of laid paper, ruled in gray on recto. Inscribed in black ink, with extensive revisions in the same ink and in pencil. After further revision these verses became section 2 of the published version. Leaf 4 ("Blow, trumpeter, free and clear—I/ follow thee,"): on a leaf of laid paper, gray-ruled on recto (see 6-7). Inscribed in black ink, with revisions in the same, in pencil, and in orange crayon. Whitman's orange-crayon note "Serenity—cool fresh/ placidity—" runs lengthwise up the left margin to the top of the page. After further revision these verses became section 3 of the published version. Leaf 5 ("Blow again trumpeter—and let/ the notes swell high,"): on one leaf of white wove paper, ruled in blue on verso. Three sets of pinholes appear in the upper left corner. Inscribed in black ink, with revisions in the same. This is an early draft of lines Whitman would revise and expand in Leaf 6 to eventually form section 4 in the published version. Leaf 6 ("Blow again, trumpeter, and/ for my sensuous eyes"): on the same paper as leaves 4 and 7. Inscribed partly in black ink and partly in pencil; the ink section is revised in the same ink, in pencil, and in pink ink; the pencil section is revised in pencil, in brown-black ink (fine pen), and in pink ink. The pencil lines are written below the pencil note "see last part of Consuelo vol 5th," by which Whitman apparently meant the novel Consuelo by George Sand, a book from which he made frequent borrowings. This was a later draft of lines on leaf 7; the number "4" appears in orange crayon at the top of the leaf. Leaf 7 ("Blow again, trumpeter and/ bring before me now,"): on a leaf of the same paper as leaves 4 and 6. Inscribed in black ink, with revisions in the same, in brown ink, and in pink ink. At the foot of the leaf Whitman wrote the parenthetical note "(see last vol. of Consuelo)" with a cartoon hand pointing to it; at this point he revised the ink lines on leaf 6, consulted Consuelo, and drafted his new pencil verses on the other leaf. Leaf 8 ("Blow again trumpeter and/ for thy theme..."): on the verso of a leaf of Department of Justice letterhead (see leaves 1-2), inscribed in black ink, with revisions in pink ink and then black ink. The pink ink was mostly applied with a broader nib here than in earlier leaves. Whitman's note "the piece must move on/ not lag/ sentimental" runs up the left margin to the top of the page. These trial verses, many of them incomplete, were revised to form section 5 in the published version of the poem. Leaf 9 ("Blow again trumpeter/ and give/ for me/ now/ Thy war notes' magic spell"): on a leaf of white wove paper, blue-ruled on verso. Multiple pinholes in the center-left portion of the leaf. Inscribed and revised in black ink. In the lower right corner of the leaf appears a cryptic blue-crayon note in Whitman's hand: "Hah!"
  - "Ned, A Phantasy," 1881 May 15, AMs, 4 pp. on 4 l., #3829 (Bowers #28). (Box-folder 1:60)
  - "A new doctrine," n.d., AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:61)
    From "Notes on the Meaning and Intention of 'Leaves of Grass,'" sections 65. Includes "Other writers/poets look on..."
  - "A Night Battle, Over a Week Since," n.d., AMs rough draft, 2 pp. on 2 l., Barrow. #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:62)
    From "Specimen Days."
  - "Of all themes and of each...," [ca. 1876], AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 5.5 cm. x 19.5 cm., #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:63)
    Beginning "Of all themes and of each" contains draft lines written in pencil. The relationship between the draft lines and Whitman's published verse is unknown.
  - "Of Biography and of all literature and art," [ca 1857-1859], AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 21.5 x 12 cm., #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:64)
    On one full Williamsburgh tax blank (21.5 x 12 cm.), with the corners cropped diagonally, and with two corrections in bright pink ink. Two sets of pinholes in center. These prose notes evidently preceded To a Literat.— (see below) in the composition of the poem. The ideas were incorporated in section 2 of the 1860 version.
  - "Old Age echoes," [1891], AMsS, 1 p. on 1 l. with attached woodcut engraving, #3829 (Bowers #9-10). (Box-folder 1:65)
    Written in ink on two leaves of paper pasted together to form one long leaf. The general title appears to be Old Age Echoes, but beneath that title are the two poems under which titles the item is catalogued: Sounds of the Winter and The Unexpress'd. Pasted to the leaf below the second poem is a woodcut engraving of Walt Whitman along with his autograph. Under that is what has been classified as two lines from an unidentified poem. A note at top states, "intended to make one page."
  - "Old Age's Lambent Peaks," [ca. 1880's], AMsS, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 25 cm. x 20.5 cm., Barrow, #3829-a. (Box-folder 1:66)
    Note at top states "sent to Century accepted—paid." Written in ink.
  - "On Samuel Johnson," [ca. 1857], AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, #9778 item 2. (Box-folder 1:67)
    With typed transcription.
  - "On Shakespeare and Ben Jonson" [ca.1850] (Box-folder 1:68)
  - "On Shakespeare and his Sonnets and Edmund Spencer," [ca. 1850], AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, #9778 item 3. (Box-folder 1:69)
  - "On the Composition of Leaves of Grass (Large parts of the poems...)," n.d., AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, #9778. (Box-folder 1:70)
    A description in third person, with a number of deletions and corrections, of his manner of composing Leaves of Grass.